Inventory of the George Washington Parke Custis Papers, 1832-1856
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Materials, 1855-1856., 15 items. (Folder 3)
  - George W[ashington]; P[arke] Custie, "Arlington House," [Arlington, Virginia], to Francis Nelson, [New Kent County, Virginia], 17 Jan[uar]y 1855., 4 pages. ALS. (Folder 3)
    Notes that the decision to run the r[ail] road by the "White House" will be made tomorrow; instructs Nelson to give them te land necessary for the bridge's abatement and any other needed right-of-way, for the railroad will be a "decided benefit," allowing him to sell his fish almost fresh in Richmond noting that the rent for a fishery along the Potomac had risen from $133 1/3 a year to $4000; crops will not go to Richmond, but to West Point or Baltimore, where he has had satisfactory dealings and where higher prices compensate for the distance; reports that he wants to own no more "Negro property," of which he has $100,000 worth; notes that a gentleman in "Washington City" congratulated him for selling his Lower Country Wheat Crop for $17,000; says he knows nothing of it and begs Nelson to send information.
  - George W[ashington]; P[arke] Custis, "Arlington House," [Arlington, Virginia], to Francis Nelson, "White House, near New Kent C[ourt] H[ouse], Virginia," 26 Jan[uar]y 1855., 3 pages. ALS. (Folder 3)
    Acknowledges that he [Nelson] has quadrupled his property's production since becoming agent; wishes work to commence on the mill; notes the unpleasantness of some of the correspondence and asks for information regarding the sale of last year's wheat crop, noting that he had received $6000 and wondered if any of the remainder could be remitted to him; refers to having been insulted by being arrested for a debt of which he knew nothing.
  - Account Sheet of Major G[eorge] W[ashington]; P[arke] Custis, listing agricultural supplies purchased, 20 March 1855-19 June 1856., 1 page. D. (Folder 3)
  - George W[ashington]; P[arke] Custis, "Arlington House" [Arlington, Virginia], to Francis Nelson, "White House, near New Kent C[ourt] H[ouse], Virginia," 9 April 1855., 3 pages. ALS. (Folder 3)
    Reports that Col. [Robert E.] Lee can't look over his accounts as he has received his new commission; has retained a lawyer and a banker to look over accounts; requests that Nelson submit the dates of the receipts for money credited to him [GWPC]; Wheat prospects are $2.30-$2.45 with new crops engaging $2.00; Bishop [William] Meale to visit White House and will report to {GWPC] on his holdings; wants complete list of all Negroes' ages; health as usual, depressed in spirits.
  - George W[ashington]; P[arke] Custis, "Arlington House." [Arlington, Virginia], to Francis Nelson, "White House, near New Kent C[ourt] H[ouse], Virginia," 12 July 1855., 2 pages. ALS. (Folder 3)
    Notes that Mr. Raoch has returned from the "White House" lauding the size of the oat and corn crops; finds it "remarkable" that some acres are producing 30 bushels of wheat and notifies him [Nelson] that he will take $2 cash [a bushel] for the wheat; recommends Mr. Roach as a contractor; hopes that the railroad will not delay any longer.
  - Richmond and York River Railroad Company, Richmond, [Virginia], to George W[ashington]; P[arke] Custis, 18 August 1855., 2 pages. (Folder 3)
    PDS, informing Custis of a Commissioners' meeting in King William County for ascertaining a just compensation for landowners along the railroad line; ADS, [on reverse] Custis empowering Nelson to act on his behalf at the Commissioners' meeting.
  - George W[ashington]; P[arke] Custis, "Arlington House," [Arlington, Virginia], to Francis Nelson, "White House, near New Kent C[ourt] H[ouse], Virginia," 22 August 1855., 2 pages. ALS. (Folder 3)
    Notifying him [Nelson] that he is to receive just compensation from the railraod for any right-of-way and expressing the hope that the RR will take action on the condemnation of the White House depot; asks about wheat crop and whether two barrels of clothes "for the Negroes" arrived; complains of "severe attack of diarrhea."
  - George W[ashington]; P[arke] Custis, "Alington House" [Alexandria, Virginia], to Francis Nelson, "White House, near New Kent C[ourt] H[ouse], Virginia," 7 Sept[ember] 1855., 2 pages. ALS. (Folder 3)
    Acknowledges receiving $4000 and figures that he [Nelson] must have procurred at least $2 [a bushel]; hopes for a good corn crop; tells him to look after his interest at the meeting of Railroad commissioners.
  - George W[ashington]; P[arke] Custis, "Arlington House" [Arlington, Virginia], to Francis Nelson, "White House, near New Kent C[ourt] H[ouse], Virginia," 26 Feb[ruar]y 1856., 3 pages. ALS. (Folder 3)
    Col. [Robert E.] Lee has looked over accounts and Mr. Overton Winston of Hanover will attempt to settle all unsettled accounts no further expenditures; encourages him to market fish noting that fish has increased by five- hundred percent and fishery rent from $133 1/3 in [GWPC's] time to $3750; "The severe season and fall of prices" will necessitate selling the corn in March.
  - George W[ashington]; P[arke] Custis, "Arlington House," [Arlington, Virginia], to Francis Nelson, "White House, near New Kent C[ourt] H[ouse], Virginia," 8 April 1856., 1 page. ALS. (Folder 3)
    Instructs him to ship the corn crop to McKonkey in Baltimore to sell.
  - George W[ashington]; P[arke] Custis, "Arlington House." [Arlington, Virginia], to Francis Nelson, "White House, near New Kent C[ourt] H[ouse], Virginia," 26 June 1856., 2 pages. ALS. (Folder 3)
    Informs Nelson that "as the time of year is at hand when it is customary in Virginia to give notice of the "discontinuance of employment," his [Nelson's] services will no longer be required after the harvest [six months], wants to sell wheat to make payment of $1000 to Mary Nelson; discusses negotiations with the railroad.
  - George W[ashington]; P[arke] Custis, "Arlington House," [Arlington, Virginia], to Francis Nelson, "White House, [near] New Kent C[ourt] H[ouse], Virginia," 18 Aug[u]st 1856., 3 pages. ALS. (Folder 3)
    Complains of marketing wheat crop at a time of "sudden and great depression of prices"; wants all crops to be shipped to Baltimore; corn prices are "looking up" instructs him to exact compensation for any of his [GWPC's] men and/or materials that the railroad uses.
  - George W[ashington]; P[arke] Custis, "Arlington House," [Arlington, Virginia], To Henry C. Wise, Drummond Town, Accomac[k] County, Virginia, 15 Oct[obe]r 1856., 2 pages. Positive pst. of ALS. (Folder 3)
    Expresses support for his [HCW's] plan to establish the Ocean Bathing Place on the coast of Virginia, noting that an advantage of such an arrangement might be that "gentlemen will not be liable...to be first knocked down and sued afterwards by coloured gentlemen."
  - George W[ashington]; P[arke] Custis, "Arlington House" [Arlington, Virginia], to Francis Nelson, "White House, [near] New Kent C[ourt] H[ouse], Virginia," 2 Nov[embe]r 1856., 2 pages. ALS. (Folder 3)
    Wheat prices are $1.50 to $1.55 while corn is at $2.00; had expressed desire to go to the Richmond fair but discouraged by family because he knew no one there; attended the "Great Exhibition at Philadelphia as Vice President of the United States Agriculture [?] Society for Virginia"; called it "grandest spectacle"; looks forward to "bright das" for lower Virginia with the extension of the new railroad to West Point, [Virginia].
  - D. R. Thomason, New York, [New York], to Francis Nelson, [New Kent County, Virginia], 23 Dec. [18]56., 2 pages. ALS. (Folder 3)
    Offers to furnish laborers for the work to be done by the railroad [subcontracted by Nelson GWPC's property] at the rate of $9 for each man, $5 passage, $2 provisions, $1 fee for laborers and for Nelson.